welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
welcome to the stoah where we explore
the knife's edge of this moment I'm AJ
bond I will be facilitating the
interview today on a topic that is very
much at my knife's edge in my life right
now and our guest is Brad Blanton who is
a psychotherapist and an author speaker
workshop runner he is the author of I
believe you said Brad seven and a half
books including the bestseller which is
the topic of today's session radical
honesty and Brad just to kind of get
started I'd love to hear how you're
doing right now and I'm also I have this
curiosity how someone who practices
radical honesty even goes about
answering that all too ubiquitous
question how are you well I'm pretty
good make a comparison about days have
been better and days have been worse I'm
kind of obsessed with the news and I
usually end up getting depressed and
pissed off every night or every other
night Trikuta Tuesdays and Thursdays but
it doesn't work too well I like watching
the news I think there's some ones
contributing a lot to my wealth these
days his name is Donald Trump because
he's such a shining example of the
opposite of what it is that teach about
so he's a poster child for what not to
do mm-hmm I love that there's a little
thing to all this yeah so that book
sales is quadrupled in the last three
years the last year radical honesty
arises here and in Europe altogether
we've done over 100 workshops in a year
in 10 different countries and three
languages and basically we're growing in
number and influence and
world is coming toward us people are
getting tired of being lied to you and
bullshitted in Condon novels it's about
to end that people are talking about it
differently yeah it's very much alive in
my life right now one of the other
facilitators in this group actually
mentioned radical aliveness and he's
here Tyson and when I heard that phrase
I was like that's what I want in my life
maybe you could give us a bit of an
introduction like what what is radical
honesty mean for you hmm well radical
honesty was the the first time my book
came out was called telling the truth it
was in hardback and it didn't do that
great and I went to a few book
conventions and started learning
something about marketing and what a
word would rephrase that used in it but
hadn't put in the title was radical
honesty when I changed the title to
radical honesty how to transform your
life by telling the truth it became a
best-seller
because before everybody thought they
knew about telling the truth but nobody
thought they knew anything about radical
honesty so basically I started watching
how I said things and saying them
uncovering more the general idea is that
if you're willing to share what you
notice that you are acknowledging there
by that noticing is more important than
thinking and that thesis that noticing
is more important than thinking is
throughout the whole series of radical
honesty books mmm-hmm so it's let me see
if I can completely get this it we're
kind of our culturally predisposed to
over think as opposed to just really
noticing what is actually happening in
this moment is that accurate
yeah but almost anything is overthinking
we
our whole culture our whole tradition is
to overvalue thinking and part of what
we say is that thinking itself is not as
important period as we think it is is
there's something about thinking that
leads us towards dishonesty there is
implicitly likely to lead you away from
honesty in the sense that you're more
concerned the further you go into your
ideation the more you're concerned about
the performance of the idea and the more
concerned you are about convincing other
people's about right you are and so
forth so that basically we have a model
of awareness which is that you can take
everything you can possibly be aware of
in your life and easily divided into
three categories you can notice what's
going on in front of you right now that
is what you see here and stuff like that
you can also be aware of what's going on
within the confines of your own skin
right now like some at like feeling with
so much stuff yeah and you can also be
aware of what you're thinking and that's
all there is there isn't anymore
we call it inside outside upside down
and this we call upside down because
usually it's bullshit something about
like just observing what is as opposed I
guess as you said anytime I start
thinking it's an interpretation it's a
story it's an analysis it's it's getting
away from just observing yes that's
right it's at least a step or two away
because as when you start noticing
you're noticing you can sort of judge
how much time you primarily focused on
thinking and how much time are you
focused on noticing your body and how
much time have you focused on noticing
things outside of you and are you one
important dimension that Fritz Perls
taught me I was trained in Gestalt
therapy and okay and one of the things
he used to stress was the in addition to
him thinking that
difference between noticing and thinking
was that noticing was much more
important but one of the things that the
extract in that he stressed a lot was
that if you are in contact with someone
else the quality of the communication is
much more intense and if you're
withdrawn from someone else it's much
less intense and so he talked about a
dimension called contact and withdrawal
oh and I was reveal aberrated on it so
that I say visual contact is you're not
looking each other right now
verbal contacts are speaking to each
other right now and so forth so there's
the visual contact verbal contact
ideational contact so you can be I can
be speaking to you not looking at you so
I can be partially in contact with you
but not as fully in contact and what
I've based on 35 years of practice of
psychotherapy in Washington DC where the
largest majority of my clientele were
lawyers I had to actually naturally
become an expert in lying or I wouldn't
be able to have a practice language yes
that's right and I did a lot of work
writing about couples and about child
rearing and one of my favorite books is
called radical parenting because what I
tell parents of young kids is what you
have to teach your child is not as
important as what they have to teach you
they know that what they remind you of
that you forgot is much more valuable to
you and to them via you than anything
you've got to teach them so instead of
going out there and trying to gear up
with what they need to know and put
forces on them
you should just touch their feet and say
what should I do to serve you today
master
what's coming up for me is that the
beauty of a child's just it really is a
kind of radical honesty like they just
say it and yeah we as a culture say
honey like don't say that and I go to
the store and I think it's like a we
slowly condition that radical honesty
out of them and I hear you saying that
actually it's an opportunity for them to
recondition us yes
it's an opportunity to rest remind what
we forgot when we're thinking about it
instead of really being with it in a
memory mm-hmm so there's a couple like
little roads that I really want to go
down and I just want to say for those
who are joining us feel free to put some
questions in the chat anytime they come
up and I'll keep an eye on them and
pepper them in and for the last half
we'll go to you guys and and open it up
but put the questions in the chat and
that way we can keep the conversation
going while the questions are kind of
building up I'm wondering Brad you
talked about being a psychotherapist for
a bunch of lawyers was there like a an
epiphany moment for you like was there
what was the catalyst in that
environment where you were like okay
it's gotta be about radical honesty or
it's got to be about telling the full
truth I'm wondering what the what the
birth was of this idea it wasn't just
one AHA experience it was a whole bunch
and I was also part of my background as
I got in the civil rights movement in
Texas and throughout the South when I
was 19 years old which was 1959 I'll be
80 at a few months basically
I spent a lot of time in the civil
rights movement I did get shot at red
bike bombed and put in jail arrested 15
times or so and basically I also was a
hippie and I started taking acid when I
was 20 and did lots of LSD and basically
all of us knew who were about 30 when we
said don't trust anyone over 30 we met
it even after we were over 30
and has something to do with realizing
that people in positions of authority
are not authoritative that generally
they're just as full of shit as they can
be and that now and then if they're not
completely full of shit they're mostly
full of shit
and so that entered into you the way
that I did therapy to you if people were
not willing to tell the truth in their
relationships to other people I just
said that's in I'm not singing in
therapy go find another therapist who
doesn't know what the job is and after I
had done that for about 20 years I
finally wrote a book about it so there
was this like inherent distrust of the
man of the system because of what was
happening culturally at that time and it
sounds like that bled in to your
practice and you're just like yeah I
mean it's almost like some of your
clients might have represented that
authority and what an exciting
opportunity for you to confront them and
say your bullshit won't stand like it's
it's not yeah a lot of their lawyers are
so retired when you retire at 30 it's
got like the possibility of a new career
yeah when these are gone I was just
gonna say that the life of sharing what
you notice when you feel free to tell
things that are not conventionally
considered okay to talk about is a very
nourishing life you feel like you're
able to relate to people in ways you
haven't been before and then it serves
as an invitation and that invitation is
very attractive to other people so that
we started having little communities of
people who grew up around what I ran a
place called the Center for wellbeing
and the community just grew up naturally
because when people finished with
therapy in about a year or so we talked
about what they got but they would also
come around we would do workshop or
something because they liked sharing
what they'd learned with other people so
it became ran more and more group
therapy groups and more
workshops and eventually I designed a
workshop called the eight-day workshop
which was to give people the benefits of
the year of psychotherapy and eight days
intensive workshops and there's a free
radical honesty like this was just a
building up to that this was during the
evolution of radical honesty that
writing up a lot of that was what the
book radical honesty came out in 94 I
think
who's that I imagine there's a
contagious quality you start being more
honest your peers start being more
honest their families start being more
honest and it kind of ripples out from
there
good that's yeah it does we have a
bumper sticker which is an attempt to do
what we call honest marketing and the
bumper sticker says radical honesty it
works pretty good most of the time
that's the extent of our PR effort you
feel like there's like a radical honesty
about radical honesty that sort of sees
the limitations of radical oh yeah yeah
some people pissed off not whatever talk
to you again won't agree to keep being
honest so basically we have what we call
this very compassionate philosophy
called fuck them if they can't take a
joke how do people react like yeah I'm
like the reason why this is so alive for
me Brad
is that I come from a very waspy family
I call it customer service that's are
different it's like I see it
the customer's always right and everyone
is the customer and you know I'm just
constantly being nice and agreeing and
people pleasing her and in my mind
radical honesty would really offend my
Canadian waspy culture and and I think I
desire it but I'm afraid good if you say
that to a group of people who are even
waspy they will know what you mean
right and you know they'll know what you
mean because you've been doing it too
and you know that there's a certain
constraint on you that's there day and
night all throughout your whole life
which you don't really like you would
rather have the more unconstrained kind
of like childlike innocence that allows
you to say I don't know when you don't
know or no I don't want to do that for
I'm mad at you or it's things like that
like now to hell with you I'm not doing
that
oh my god that's terrible but it's not
so bad it's the beginning of an honest
conversation
mm-hmm-hmm like the theory behind it is
so clear I guess what I'm seeing is I'm
wondering if people like me and a lot of
people getting started need a kind of
entryway like a kick in the pants it's
like you want they just what's the thing
that gets the ball rolling so that you
can do it or is it really just just
fucking do it well what people usually
complain about is the fact that it may
be confrontational or offensive but
what's most scary about it is that
you're vulnerable when you do that you
open up it's kind of instead of having
your life oriented around defending
yourself or your reputation in the minds
of other people you say you you're my
reputation in your mind it may be good
or bad that's not the main thing I'm
going for what I'm going for is telling
you what I appreciate what I resent what
I like what I don't like what I'm about
in the world rather than and whether I
like you or don't like you whether I
want you like me or not like me then I'm
going to talk about that I'm gonna go a
cut deeper I'll tell you what's going on
for me what I noticed going through my
mind is what I notice in my sensations
in my body and what I notice about you
and so that when you're talking to me
it's kind of a dangerous thing because
it's a little bit threatening to the
usual role playing it's more intimate
than people are used to tolerating
do you find that there are some
techniques aside from just being really
honest to help invite that person to
join you at that level because I think
my fear is that I'll be honest and the
person will just be like you know and
it's like I'm like I want to know I want
to see you as well I want some gravy
here on the vulnerability front I think
well then your next step it honestly to
be my imagining is that you're not being
completely and there's always there
there if the answer is my question it's
like just right say it exactly that's it
you got alright you're on the first rung
that three more years she could be a
radical honesty trainer I I hope to be
that in a de-facto way at very many all
right good I mean the topic that I am
the most fascinated by as many people
here already know is is shame and when I
think of shame it's a moderator it's
like my I've got my honesty and my truth
and then shame comes in and completely
moderates it all as to what's
appropriate what's good what's bad
what's gonna help what's gonna hurt and
it seems to me like shame is a is the if
if not one of the biggest kind of
barriers to radical honesty I wonder if
that's something that resonates with you
it resonates quite a bit yes the thing
is that what you
allow some limited set of sensations
which at the base level shame is
sensation based do you feel something in
your bodies is increase of heart rate
your blush mm-hmm and flush in the front
of your chest and your face and you feel
warmth and your body and place is
different you do and you want to use
turn away and not be in the spotlight of
attention and so one of the things that
we work with with people is that when
you are willing to experience an
experience it comes and goes
but when you resist an experience it
persists yeah and one of the things that
causes the resistance of the resistance
of shame is that people resist being
ashamed and and you can just say well
I'm feel warmth in my face and imagine
my face is red and I guess mine
imagining is that I'm ashamed of what I
just said to you and I feel skirted like
I want to twitch around and move around
in you stay with that experience and
every single second you stay with it
longer like extra 10 seconds with it you
find that is just a bunch of sensations
uh-huh and that what we say another one
of our sneakers is life is just
sensational when life is just
sensational
and what happens is if you're willing to
be completely naked and bare-assed
exposed one of the things we do in the a
day workshop is about the third day
everybody has to take off all their
clothes is that true yeah and then they
have to stand up in front of the group
one person at a time
and talk about their body and point out
what they're ashamed of and what they're
proud of where their scars came from and
they look at the other people and they
walk around and talk to them and people
walk around talk people really know they
have to do that with the workshop cost
like 15
fifteen hundred three thousand dollars
begins on when you do get but basically
you don't get to go to the workshop
unless you agree that you'll do that yet
stand naked in front of people talk
about it and you get videotaped when
you're talking about your body and then
the next day we ask him to come back in
and watch sit next to the screen and
watch their own videotape and then tell
us what their reaction is to watching
themselves naked on videotape talking
about their bodies and so what we learn
from this is that people so dreaded in
their there was some people didn't do
the workshop and also stuff they would
read it and read it and then actually
went through the experience the next
three or four days of the workshop we
have to keep saying put your goddamn
clothes on put your clothes back on
because we couldn't get people to quit
being naked because actually not having
anything to have to hide anymore is such
a relief and it's so funny when people
are laughing and we often say in that
group
I'm not laughing with you I'm laughing
at you because people get to kind of
enjoy shame and it runs it as it runs
shame as a motivating force people think
well you deadbeat you'd be ashamed if
you did that yeah probably let's see God
see viewer because it wouldn't be like a
life-threatening thing Brad this sounds
like a great stoah session I'm going to
take it over zoom yeah it's kind of hard
to be close enough over zoomed it be
embarrassing in that to be worth
mm-hmm-hmm Wow I really love that thank
you for that insight I have a couple
questions that are coming up in the text
that I want to send your way one of them
is have you ever pushed radical honesty
too far and regretted it like is there
some some is there some such thing as
too honest would be those feelings are
hurt I stay with them until they
experience they've heard enough to let
it go and sometimes they're triggered
into anger and I asked him to experience
the anger and to resent me for what I
did or to say you hurt my feelings or to
cry they feel sad and to stay with the
experience the whole point of it is that
rat Agosti covers a multitude of sins
but the purpose of the sins is to not
have them the avoidance of such things
that are triggered in you from what
happened to you earlier in your life to
have that not be the theme of your life
that you can actually design and
influence what your life is about only
if you are able to inhibit just being
run by triggers there's something gets
triggered and so you behave a certain
way because you learned how to do that
when you were five and a half or a nine
or something like that and you just
reenact that without any consciousness
yeah and what happens when people start
sharing other people are honest with
them and people end up being moved with
each other so they people cry a lot in
these groups I cry a lot I'm a big sissy
and they jab me better at all time it
didn't bother me but the idea is that
you have the experiences that you have
and you live them out loud and you share
them with other people and so when
you're vulnerable you're vulnerable and
when you're angry you're angry and you
get angry and you tell you get over it
doesn't take about 90 seconds mm-hmm and
you get hurt and you get over it and so
you you have some kind of a way of
saying to somebody that's okay if you
hurt my feelings I'll be hurt and I'll
get over it instead of like staying
alienated from you for 20 years because
you hurt my feelings I'm there back here
in 1993 there does seem to be something
powerful about you you need someone
there to be honest too
so it's like it seems important as you
said to stay with the person to
yeah I'm angry yeah I'm pissed off yeah
you're angry but let's stay in community
until we're back to a kind of connection
or equilibria exactly yeah exactly and
also be more and more specific so it may
start out just well you're an asshole
and I don't like you that's good that's
better nothing but then we try to get
down to the eggs I resent you for saying
I should read that book I don't read
that goddamn book I tried to read it I
resent you for saying that good some of
your smaller but petty or resentment
started coming out it turns out after
we've been at night they were shopping
everybody has to admit that we're all
petty we're all just petty little
nitpicking little nasty little bitches
and bastards and and and it's also
pretty funny because when it's shared
you know you mean you actually got up
and left Thanksgiving and didn't go to
nicely dinner anymore just because
someone quit therefore down too hard
when they were mad yes I did well your
whole life is run by this kind of
reactions then I guess mm-hmm it's
occurring to me that self-awareness
obviously has to be a big piece of this
puzzle be in order to be able to like
I'm assuming you want to take those
triggers and put them into your
consciousness by saying I'm noticing a
trigger I'm noticing of this but for a
lot of people it's really hard to decide
enta fie from that is it just about the
axis or is it is there some tools there
well it is hard to dissident if I wasn't
that but it's also very rewarding to get
over things like like when you used to
be afraid to say the boss no I don't
want to do that and you say to the boss
to the first time no I don't want to do
that and resent you for every goddamn
time you ask me to do it to know you had
that in you and you say I didn't either
and what happens is there's a different
level
conversation do you find that there's
you talked about that petty resentment I
I imagine there's a backlog that's built
up and the first time you practice
radical honesty in like a situation like
that you kind of have to say and there's
a backlog like there's a lot of
resentment I wish I had it you know you
want to clear the slate yeah and if you
are open to them clearing their slate
with you right then the whole
relationship for both of you is changed
and in a more nourishing direction where
you feel heard and seen and known and
talked to and they do tea and it's that
deeper level of intimacy that I'm saying
we need like right now during this
crisis it's just you can't watch TV at
night without seeing instances of it
there's this new strange new normal is
going to get born here and the new
normal is going to require more honesty
because radical honesty is going to be
is becoming obvious you know whenever an
expert says something and then Donald
Trump says something on top of it this
the reverse and you say well who should
I believe the political authority or the
scientists the question about who's
believable or not is pretty obvious and
what's happening is there's there is the
change in the culture where we don't
want to be cheered up with some kind of
false bullshit happy-happy talk that's
just bullshit in the first place I'm not
interested in being treated like a child
to be controlled in some kind of like
jail I don't want to live in the jail of
a mind that says watch out be careful
don't offend anybody tiptoe through your
whole life act like your whole life is
on eggshells and try to get through to
the end without being too embarrassed
and what I want me to say is fuck that
I'm not interested in that
oh and
and people who do do that resent the
hell out of it and they're not very
happy when they're acting happy
I know that yeah so I'm gonna open it up
now
there's a lot of really cool questions
and why don't I let the question askers
actually ask their questions I asked one
of them already but I just wanted the
next question Raven I'd love for you to
ask your question but before you do I
just want to preface that in the digital
world we live in there's a lot of
opportunities for one-sided honesty
where you do a podcast that's really
honest or you do zoom classes that are
really honest and I have noticed that it
creates these one-sided connections
where people know almost too much about
you sometimes and I feel like that
really connects with Ravens question so
why don't you jump in Raven you can just
unmute yourself
sure hi thank you for being here Brad
hey thank you yeah so my question is
about the role of the private is there a
role of the private or privacy in in
your framework of radical honesty or our
automatic inclination is to withhold but
what I say in radical honesty is that
the most pernicious form of lying is
just not saying what you know so that
it's being featured these days and the
whole conversation worldwide about the
virus is have Wendy withhold information
and and the the most deadly thing we've
done as a species with this virus is
delay the sharing of information that
was available by just two or three weeks
killed thousands and thousands of people
and the the the attempt to preserve
something in your imagination you want
to preserve some people's impression of
you usually you want to make sure you
preserve a good impression in the mind
of other people and what you would risk
if you said well I don't know what do
you think of me to them you'd be like
leaving it open for them to make their
own independent judgment without you
controlling it in some way and when you
do that what comes from other people
mostly is gratitude because I think well
thank you for asking I'm glad you want
to know I appreciate us having the
conversation better rather than just
trying to make a good impression and
then make me like you it's the reason
that I called radical honesty sort of an
overall rubric is because when you keep
being honest you're honest about how
you're honest the last time and they're
honest about what their reaction was
last time and then you start being
honest about what you didn't be honest
about the last time and then what
happened
as you feel mostly gratitude because
you're known by them and you know them
and you accept and value each other and
it's not just that they con you into
liking you it's that they actually
appreciate you for what you are actually
like and what you actually said it is
and that's much more nurturing than just
getting an applause for them for
performance
Reno I really like your second question
about the life experiences the writing
why don't you ask that
hey thank you so my question was it's my
understanding that the writing process
becomes a sort of therapeutic process
for authors and what I wanted to know is
what you've learnt about yourself while
writing radical honesty
that's a good question come up with an
answer I had a moment when I was writing
the book radical I see about the middle
of it I realized that I hadn't said why
I was writing that book
and it was a background motivating force
for me but I wasn't sure he was people
so just started writing the reason I'm
writing this book I want to build my
reputation in the minds of other people
I want to become famous you know what
people think I'm smart and a wise man
and to buy my books and give me praise
and give me a lot of money I'm greedy
and I won't have that so I went on until
I got tired of it that I hated it a
little bit but I left it the book and it
turned out that lots and lots of people
when they got that part of the book
wrote me letters and have it since then
like send emails and lots of other
things they really appreciated that I
just sort of stumbled onto that and then
went ahead in the laboratory then that
was in the book because I was being
honest about wanting to get attention
and be famous and to have an impact and
I wanted to help people I have lots of
themes of helping people and I have
helped a lot of people I think and
that's basically what I learned to do so
every now and then when I'm writing
something goes across like that and I
just say whatever it is as best I can
so that my performance for me is to
perform not performing thank you wow
that last line you just said Brad about
performing not performing brings up
something that Peter and I have been
discussing about when we're trying to be
authentic is it authentic or is it more
like our best approximation of
authenticity our best approximation of
noticing you know what I mean like is
there is there some degree of
performance but it's like a performance
rooted as hard as you can in reality no
we're good we're we're not perfectly
anti perfectionism but we're against it
I have this saying I ask people to
recite anything worth doing is worth
doing poorly and I like people having
say that over and over again because
it's built in as I say what anything
worth doing is worth doing well was the
known dictum that I say go ahead and
proceed when you don't know what you're
doing that's better because the
protection racket you're building when
you're making sure you get it right
before you say it is withholding from
other people it's keeping the
information from flowing and it's like
experts are being able to say I don't
know you know when people ask me
questions I'm not supposed to say I
don't know and I look for opportunity to
say damn fine Oh what do you think
because I like what people when people
ask questions you know they have that
answer implicit in there right right
it's refreshing
you'll had a really interesting question
about certain substances Daniel do you
want to come on and ask your question
yeah perfect if you can hear me I just
pulled over so am i coming in yeah we
can yeah awesome hey Brad I met you with
her Jean in New York City years ago you
do with the Rob Roz if you remember yeah
it was great to see you and thanks for
all your work I just see it trickling
all over the world and my events it's an
honor to talk to you briefly here well I
remember one of the things I remember
about our conversation was how you were
making kind of fun of yourself that you
liked pot and alcohol a little too much
and through many of my years including
myself I love pot I really love it
but for some reason there's just like I
feel like there's been an underlying
guilt that bubbles up around that
especially if I had a really good time
like if I smoked pot and had the best
time ever then like was it because the
pot or something around there mmm and I
really believe I mean including per zone
because I think person I went completely
sober that I've only started that I'm
like is that the only way to not feel
guilty about these substances is to
completely quit them or do I just think
I love the guilt more and my question to
you is can you relate and if you have
kind of figured a way to be in more
harmony with those substances yourself
hmm what I was just talking about about
anything worth doing is worth doing
poorly is that what are the things that
I'm writing a book right now called
contact and withdrawal and it talks
about that now you can be in verbal
contact in physical contact and we can
shake hands with each other yeah I'd
speak to each other we have all these
different kinds of contact and then we
can turn them and walk away from each
other and walk out the door and we've
withdrawn and one of the things that
trills and I used to talk about a lot
was having clean contact and clean
withdrawal so that you can contact
someone you're completely with them and
then you go you're gone the hell away
and that what are the things that I like
about being stoned a lot of the time is
that I don't particularly care about how
my performance is going when I'm stoned
I'm just laughing around playing music
or we're singing together or something
like that and he gets so wrapped up in
the very sensations of it now I find it
to be good for that grounding and
sensations in the body that form of
grounding so I like it so I I ran for
Congress about eight or nine years ago
and the reporters would ask me have you
ever used any illegal substances I said
I've done every illegal drug known to
man I would get really frustrated
because they had all these shocking
questions and I know the answer to I
made it I sort of you know I'd shut up
here when I'd done all these things and
I talked about them not with that shame
and they just became bored and walked
off and the thing is that if you don't
have to hide something if it's not a bad
thing if you're it's not something that
shame is running for you that now and
then you might get stoned but you're not
gonna be like a STONER where you smoke
at every damn day or something and you
might have a drink down there but you're
not gonna be drunk all the time you
might get drunk once or twice a year or
something but not like falling down
drunk like a teenager or something but
you might have a drink and total joint
and then it might not do it for a week
that's what I look for something where
it's not like basically being trapped by
it because you have to avoid it because
it's a bad thing or something like that
freedom means you can do or not do
something and that each new moment of
freedom is a new opportunity so you
could say well I've I've had like a year
of sobriety and I'll ask you about what
the story was and did you what you do
beforehand and do you not do you need to
stay in a a and by the estimation and
your estimation and some people do and
some people don't
and so what I'm my main value in this is
freedom it's freedom to make mistakes
they're not so bad they kill you or hurt
somebody else and if you can moderate
them so that you stay with them as their
hurt they can get over it
then your being a kind of presence in
the world and that's what this is all
about is about being able to be a
presence in the world to be
participating in acknowledging noticing
each other and to be willing to be with
each other and nourished by being with
each other in that experience of being
theater so it's not ever really a
question should I ever smoke pot or you
know the thing is I know that altered
states of consciousness has contributed
a lot to my ability to enjoy being alive
in the world to be nurturing to other
people yeah thanks thanks for exploring
that with me it seems to be a continuous
unraveling for me and definitely feel
supported by you exploring it out loud
with me and being here with you so thank
you Brad he end up in prison branded on
me ray you had a couple really
interesting comments and a question as
well I wondered if you wanted to jump in
and ask one of them
sure I have to scroll up here I think
one question that I asked was is it ever
like inappropriate or not supportive to
be radically honest like is there ever a
time when it's just not serving the
greater good of the experience yeah I
think when if you're not clear with your
agreements about other people when
you're honest about what they've said to
you without their permission that that's
violating something about their
assumptions and yours and that you if
you're radically honest about someone
else and they have given you permission
to you need to talk to them and invite
them to do that for themselves rather
than you do it and the other thing is
I'm not like I'm not radically honest
for moral reason so much as I am for
reasons of contact for nurturance for
the benefit of people and that right and
wrong are not the main reasons for being
very close so if I smoke a joint I don't
call this year so I was there smoking a
joint over here I thought you'd be
interested I don't think it would I
don't think they would come over anyway
they'd say just your stone good so
anyway that's it that's extended my
answer that I appreciate you really
question
what's coming to shoot you for the
answer thanks ray
I'm still thinking about when you talked
about the gestalt therapy and the
connecting thing and there's been a
mention of non-violent communication in
the chat and in fact just listening to
you talk kind of reminds me of Marshall
Rosenberg and I wonder in an NBC they
have this concept of a liveness which
sounds similar it's like when you really
talk to someone honestly in the moment
about what's happening in the moment
there's this kind of amazing type of
connection and it sounds similar to what
you were talking about in terms of
Gestalt in terms of like the levels of
connecting I wonder if you if that
sounds about the same to you and if you
could talk a little bit more about that
hmm well I like him and I'm a little
prejudiced against a lot of his
followers because we had a lot of
ingratitude groups and we always have
anger to deal with anger because they're
always so I don't know that it seems to
me that it's a little to you moralistic
well that yeah there's a right way to be
nonviolent and that's you know I was in
the civil rights movement in the
nonviolent civil rights movement you
know I know that a lot of our
accomplishments that I helped
participate in I involved a threat of
violence I was I was a muse child and my
stepfather used to beat up my mother and
my brother and me and stuff and when I
was 13 and a half I took a piece of
firewood and fractured his skull broke
his ribs and put him in a hospital for a
day and we came back I told him I had
two shotguns I'd gotten and hit him out
so the next time you did anybody in this
house when I kill you and I ended up
leaving home when I was just short of 14
years old and I worked out a
relationship with my stepfather later
included going back and beating him up
one more time and in the civil rights
movement one thing that
we talked about we was thinking about
writing a book about this my friend
Booker T Bonner he's just died last year
he and I were sitting in at a restaurant
in Austin Texas after we'd integrated
the theaters and it was like 11 o'clock
the restaurant closed at night we'd been
there like for a couple of hours and
been there a couple hours the morning
we'd been sitting in there for three
months we'd go and occupy a booth and
then they wouldn't serve us and we
wouldn't have we would be blocking their
customers so he'd had like five or six
booths filled up and so I was just mad
that evening I said I'm tired of this he
said I am Tina we just went around back
the porch it was loose clothes we banged
on the door and he opened the door he
knew this very well because he were
there every day said what do you want I
said I want you to desegregate this
goddamn restaurant and come back here
kick your fucking ass and he says well
I'm oh damn me in Sweden nobody tells me
what to do and Beatty says love me
nigger nobody tells me what dude I said
I mean goddamn redneck if you don't
integrate the son of bitch I'm gonna
kick your ass he slammed or one face so
that wasn't exactly what you call a
non-violent interaction but the
surprising part was we went back the
next morning at 10 o'clock when in sent
our usual place and he comes walking in
with a pad is what can I get you and I
had to check see if I had any money cuz
we didn't expect to be actually you have
to pay for food and so I ordered a bacon
and eggs and so did BTD we had coffee
and we sat there and we ate our food and
we drank our coffee and nothing was said
except just when I paid him the check
and he handed with a change back I
looked at him and I said thank you and
he said thank you and what happened was
he was abused child - he's a big like
six foot five sweet he could have kicked
my ass I'm sure but I would have
absolutely gone after King is anyway and
he knew it because I we were both hurt
and abused children and he integrated
their restaurant and it was the only
integrated I stood for three
and everybody tried to make him not
desegregate but he was the damn main
Swede and he wasn't going to let them
tell him what to do and so a lot of our
expressions of resentment appear to be
violent but I don't agree if you don't
hit somebody in the face or something
that's not violence as far as I'm
concerned you'd say you lowlife
motherfucking son of a bitch that's
perfectly acceptable I just wanted to
get more particular about why there
isn't a bitch
and then get over it and say well you
know I'm not as mad at you that was
before he got over he finally he didn't
ever know we were serious until I
threatened to kick his ass so I think
non-violence has to be defined as either
physical violence or not cuz I don't
like the definition of violence just
using categories because it's not
intimate enough and to get over
mmm-hmm what that story I feel really
points a spotlight on the culture that's
forming around social justice issues
today and I'm not sure how much you have
your finger on that pulse but there is a
real movement towards write speak and
you're like even in your stories the N
word came up and yeah yeah when you said
the word sissy I tweaked on that like
part of me was like oh you're not
allowed to say sissy and I'm allowed to
now get offended and wondering how you
react to that new culture I just say
that God knows I'm sorry and say it
again but it it's like basically I'm a
self-righteous prick myself I know what
it is to be such a righteous fool and
I've been a righteous fool plenty of
times and I'm less righteous the older I
get the less rich as I am and I'd say
probably Lobby would say the less right
I am but the less attached to
righteousness I am because of the
nourishment that comes from sharing
honestly is so much more important than
being able to maintain the appearance of
being well behaved
mm-hm it seems now the culture is so
much about being right and I hear you
saying and I feel this especially from a
shame standpoint that being right
doesn't actually connect us right yeah
it does but then it makes us just
Republicans or just the runners or so
right it's a very it's a very tribal
thing right yeah yeah yeah
well we're we're down to like the last
five minutes so I wonder Brad maybe you
could tell us I know you have at least
seven or eight books and you've got a
new one obviously in the works
how can people connect with your work
where should we start
well there a lot of exciting things
going on this day we were planning for a
transition to building a strong online
workshop over the last four years we've
been working on it we've put together
lots of video tape from other workshops
and we have designed an online course
which you can find out about by going to
radical honesty dot-com and we have
about forty radical honesty trainers
about 15 here in this country and the
rest of them in Europe and we do
workshops various places all around the
world at least they were interrupted now
we're doing a few online workshops and
if you go to radical honesty calm it's
frequently changed and there's also our
presences on Facebook and social media
and basically you can find videotapes of
various obtuse and ignorant and funny
things that I've done and the view
embarrassing things if you look and what
happens is that there is this prejudice
in favor of laughter that we have and
there is a lot of funny people and a
part of what we assigned to people in
training to be trainers is to go and do
a stand-up comedy Saturday and just see
what it's like to get out there and try
to be funny and not have anybody laugh
because that's a real examination of
embarrassment there mm-hmm
why did you say that I thought it was
funny well it was there's no hiding in
standup I love that right I assume you
also make them do some kind of
striptease or something that sounds like
no no I think it's too easy in a
stand-up place it'd be too easy well
Brad this has been really refreshing and
I feel really inspired and I'm sure
other people here as well to start going
on this journey in a really
kind of conscious way to be more
radically honest so I want to thank you
so much for your honesty of course and
your humor and just your your presence
Thank You Sadie I really appreciate you
for this whole conversation and
everybody else today's question Steve
right what's my pleasure
so that's pretty much the end of our
session everyone thank you so much for
coming
this stoah runs on a gift economy as you
know so if you want to go to the store
dot CA you can help support it and I
also want to mention that there is
another session in about half an hour
that is on the theme of concept
unfolding I'm not entirely sure what it
is but it sounds really cool so feel
free to come back and check that out and
yeah thanks so much and thanks again
Brett okay thanks see you later see you
soon Thank You Brad you're welcome thank
you